One thing that impressed me most about
Zuck, and this is true of Bos as well,
is this is Philip Sue. He's one of the
few who have been promoted to
distinguished engineer or IC9 at Meta,
which is three levels higher than staff.
And I asked him about everything he
learned along the way. Someone that
stands out to you that consistently
impressed you. John Carmarmac obviously
legendary, right? Not only is he super
prolific in coding, he had an ability to
Oh wow. He also shared about his unique
demotion. I was eventually releveled
down from an E9 to an E7. Later he left
Meta to join OpenAI before it got big
and shared an interesting perspective on
why. The reason I joined OpenAI was what
I'd learned from working at Facebook is
I would much rather join the market
leader or nobody at all. And here's why.
He's one of the guests I was most
excited to have on. And hopefully you
see why after listening to the
conversation. Here is the full
episode. Thank you, Philip, for for
joining today. I'm so excited to ask you
all the questions I have here. I think a
lot of people are going to get value out
of it. So, yeah, let's start digging
into your career. Starting with
Microsoft. My understanding of your
career is that you sprinted through
Microsoft ladder. What do you credit
your your fast promotions to the
equivalent of Microsoft's E7 to? I think
the growth comes from a few things. One
is just I had several very good managers
and teammates who I grew a lot from. So
for instance, when I joined the tablet
PC team, the team was about 20 people,
but there were three distinguished
engineers on that team, which for
Microsoft terms is like very rare to
find a team like that stacked with
talent. So I learned a ton of stuff very
quickly from people on that team for
instance. I think another thing is that
I just worked very long hours is the
truth of it. Like in my first year at
Microsoft, I had a sleeping bag in my
office. I regularly slept at the office.
I would have an alarm that would wake me
up at 3:00 a.m. because I was pursuing
Da Vinci's theory that you can sleep
four hours, wake up, and then like sleep
another four hours and wake up. So, I
would wake up at 3:00 a.m., code a bit,
and then go back to sleep at 6:00 a.m.
and then wake up at 10:00 a.m. and and
keep coding, right? So, I do think a
thing that I tell people a lot is I
think there are only three main things
that contribute to fast career growth.
One is of course luck. You know, being
at the right place at the right time.
you happened to be at uh Stamford when
Sergey and Larry were working there.
They happened to pick you to join the
company, right? So, some of it is luck,
some of it is talent, you know, like
people like to say things like, "Oh,
everyone can be an astronaut." And I
don't think that that's true. Like the
harsh truth is, you know, I am never
going to be a great basketball player,
right? Like they're just things that I
cannot do. Um, similarly, someone who is
not naturally good at public speaking,
they can always improve to where they're
passable at public speaking, but they're
not going to become a Cicero through
like a lot of practice, right? So, I
think luck, talent, and the last thing I
do think is hard work. You know, if you
are willing to outwork everybody, I
think who is equally talented and
equally lucky, you're just going to get
further. Um, I am not saying that I
would recommend that to everyone. And in
fact, I do think that my work life was
way out of whack for many years there.
So, I'm not at all saying that this is
what I recommend people do, but I do
think that outworking a lot of people
goes a long
way. When you first got into the
industry, it sounds like you were really
hungry and I I was also, you know, super
motivated, too. And one thing that I
wondered though is you know when you
work so hard it trades off with your
health and then can eat into your I
guess productivity throughput um after
you lived that experience. Do you think
if your goal was growth at all costs
that that was actually optimal? Yeah,
this is a great question. And I think
there are a lot of people that will
defend the 40-hour work week with things
like, you know, when Henry Ford studied
his people, every additional hour was
like uh lower in productivity. I think
one thing people don't like to discuss
often is that I do believe your
productivity does go down on a per hour
basis as you stay up for way too long.
But I think for many people that curve
keeps going a long time before it gets
negative productivity. meaning like an
additional hour worked is actually
subtracting from your productivity. So I
feel like the truth is working 50 60
hours you will probably get a sum total
of more done but each incremental hour
is probably less effective right but I
think there's one other thing that
people don't take into account which is
you know you could say like for instance
why do surgeons still have residencies
that have 36 hour shifts right part of
it is hazing I think part of it is just
because they did it when they were young
so they're going to make you do it when
you're young right but I think another
part of it that I heard from a surgeon
is that the biggest quickest way to gain
experience in surgery is to have a lot
of surgery hours. So the more you're
there, the more you experience and if
you can pack in six years worth of
experience into four years, then you're
just going to be a better surgeon coming
out, right? And so I think although
nobody wants to be operated on by a
surgeon who's in his 34th hour, let's
say, right? Um, at the same time, you
would like a surgeon who has experienced
a very wide variety of things. So, I
think although I wouldn't recommend my
crazy work hours from when I started
work, I would say it exposed me to a lot
more experience than the average junior
person starting at Microsoft. So, there
is diminishing returns, but there are
still returns. And so, if you're a
growth at all costs career person, you
should I mean, by that logic, you should
work more. Of course, there's other
parts of life. Totally. Like if if you
were diehard convinced that career was
the most important thing for you and in
fact that you were willing to sacrifice
things like relationships and other
things like that. I do think the truth
is working longer hours is going to get
you there faster. So you grew to the
equivalent of um you know E7, my
understanding that's senior staff and
you said there were three distinguished
engineer. Is that the equivalent of E9
or would have been at at Microsoft or
Yeah, probably something like that. E9,
it's the equivalent of a vice president
level and compensation within the
company. E6 to E7, I I'm familiar with
that at Meta. Um, when you got that
promo at Microsoft, was that as a
manager or as an IC? And what's the
story behind that promo? Great question.
That was as a manager. Um, but I think I
also then became an individual
contributor at the new level as well. I
see. What made you decide to switch into
management
uh, in the first place?
I think when I was younger, I was very
ambitious for myself and I came from a
culture, you know, I'm ethnically
Chinese. I came from a culture where
people really felt like managers were
more respected and would get further in
career. And so I think I had the
somewhat misguided notion that in
software engineering becoming a manager
was the next growth step for me. So
that's largely why I became a manager.
But in my career I fluctuated between
managing people and being an individual
contributor at least six times. And I
think the main reason for that is I
really love being an individual
contributor, but I'm often asked to
manage if the team needs a temporary
manager for a while, for instance, or I
would much rather be the manager of a
team if it's poorly managed. You know
what I mean? Uh so my order of
preference would be be an individual
contributor, uh be a manager on a team
because the team doesn't have a better
manager, right? Like that's my order of
preference. But in general, I think left
to my own devices, I'd rather not manage
people. I see. And in that case where
you said if it's poorly managed, are you
saying that there's cases in your career
where the existing management was
lacking and you volunteered yourself or
you're saying someone in your management
chain said, "Philip, can you please help
us?" Yeah, both of those things have
happened before. So for instance in my
career I've had four separate times when
a previous manager of mine asked to
report to me so I became their manager
basically really and I think that yeah
uh and so that has happened four times
and I think part of that is because I've
learned from great managers you know
although I don't prefer to be a manager
I do think there are parts of what I've
learned that have been useful right and
so um I have been asked to be a manager
before um After pursuing trying to
become a manager early in my career, I
sort of stopped looking out for those
opportunities as actively as I did an
individual contributor opportunity. That
I've never heard of that before where
your manager asks to report to you. How
does that happen? Um well, I think each
situation is a little different. So on
some of the situations, they reported to
me on the same team, right? um on some
situations uh several years later they
asked to join my team you know and when
we had both moved on. So I think that in
the cases where it happened on the same
team um one time it was because the
manager wanted to be an individual
contributor on the team you know and I
was a strong individual contributor that
wanted to be a manager and so it was
almost like a swap in place right um
I've had other times several times where
I joined a different team somewhere else
and then my manager who liked working
with me was very happy to work for me as
well on the new team and so that's been
the majority of cases at some point you
get in your career, there's that
decision point of do you want to
continue down the icy track or do you
want to become a manager. What would be
your your framework of thinking through
that for for someone who's considering
that for themselves? Yeah, great
question. I personalitywise I'm very
open to new experience. So in general
I'm going to advocate for trying new
things, you know. So, I feel like in
general it can't hurt to try it if you
think that you might like it or you
think you might be good at it, but I
would put a few asterisks on. One is
like be very sensitive to whether or not
it locks you into a career you don't
want. So, for instance, I've told you
that I've switched back to an IC
probably six times in my career, right?
Um, many people cannot make that
transition, meaning they have become a
manager. Now, they're a manager of
managers. they're far away from the
code. They either are unwilling to take
a lower level job in order to be an IC,
which I'm very willing to do, right? Or
they are unable to meet the expectations
of their level as a manager as an IC.
And so I think people have to be very
careful not to accidentally walk through
a one-way door on that. For me, I've
kept that door open two ways because I
do the switch often. And when I'm
managing teams, I also love the actual
coding. So I still try to dive into the
code whenever I can. And so I've kept
both sides sort of evergreen. But I
don't think that's true of many people.
So like one is be careful that you don't
walk through a one-way door that you're
not positive that you want to walk
through, right? I think another thing
about that is people often mostly think
about themselves when they think about
wanting to be a manager. But what I
classically tell people is you are ready
to lead a team when your team would have
elected you to lead them. Right? Like
think of it this way. Would you want to
work for you? That's the key question.
Would you want to work for you? If the
answer is not a solid yes, I would be
thrilled to work for me, right? You
probably have a few things you can
improve in yourself to get to that
point. And people cannot make you the
lead of anything. Like they can
nominally make you the lead, but as you
know in software development, people can
slow roll things. People can like uh can
can sand sandbag things. Like there are
all sorts of ways your team can work
against you actually. So you need people
to want to work for you. So I think
before becoming a manager one key thing
is take a critical look at like would I
work for myself and like if not what can
I improve in myself to make it so that
people want to work for me. I think when
you have those improvements it'll be
clear and then uh people will ask you to
manage at that point. That was
interesting you talk about the two-way
doors because when I think about I made
a similar decision for myself of you
know pursuing management versus IC. I
presumed past a certain point you've
become more specialized like if I was a
manager of managers and then I switched
to my
equivalent which would be principal
engineer. those jobs are so different
that I would have thought almost no one
would be able to keep the door open. Um,
and I was thinking if I did do switches
too, I would be, I guess, resetting some
progress potentially. So, yeah, I'm
curious how you think about that. Like,
did did you ever feel like you lost
progress by switching between the two
tracks?
Yeah. Well, I definitely lost progress
and intentionally and willingly so. So,
for instance, um when I switched from
being the site director of Facebook
London to being an individual
contributor on Oculus, I was eventually
releveled down from an E9 to an E7. And
that was something that I very much sort
of wanted and I fully acknowledged was
necessary because the skills I could
demonstrate as a as a site director were
very different from the skills that were
required to be a good coder on uh on uh
Oculus. And so that was a rele bought
into it. Now many people cannot handle
that like either for ego reasons like
they feel like they can't handle it or
for compensation reasons like there are
some people whose lifestyles just grow
to fill whatever compensation they're
making right and if they refuse to uh
change their lifestyle you know they
will paint themselves into a corner
where there are increasingly less jobs
they can take because they are unwilling
uh to move. So I do think sometimes that
switch entails that movement and I also
think there are certain times in career
where that switch is easier and certain
times where that is harder. So like
here's an interesting dynamic. I think
early in career like one or two years in
uh let's say you are a software
developer you want to be a product
manager. I feel like one or two years in
it's easy to make a lateral move. You
know you're like a a junior software
developer you want to become a junior
product manager. Many people are very
willing to coach you on that. I think in
the senior, you know, E sort of fiveish
range, I feel like the transition is
very difficult. If you want to go from
an E5 software developer to an E5
product manager, just like that, I think
it will be very difficult to be good
relative to your peers. Unless your
software development work involved a lot
of product management sort of things,
right? Um, but funny enough, these
things are a diamond shape. Once you're
senior enough, the skills once again
converge. Like what is a really
effective E8 doing? Right? There are
occasionally, of course, the prodigy
coders who are just far more effective
than the average person in producing a
ton of hard code, right? But I think a
lot of very senior individual
contributors, they are actually great at
leading teams, you know, like they have
a vision for technically where the
product needs to go. They understand the
infrastructure and the weak point. They
have a plan for staged migration to the
next better design, right? And people
love working with them because they are
good and compelling at coaching others
and and whatnot. That's a lot of what
makes a great typical sort of E8 um in
in individual contributor in which case
like this diamond shape happens, right?
Which is once you're senior enough, a
lot of the skills once again overlap.
Are you good at communicating with
others? Do you have vision? Do you
understand the business strategy and how
it pertains to the technology you're
building? those things once again become
shared. So I think there's a part in the
middle where it's most difficult to make
the change. Yeah, that is a that's a
really interesting idea and I I see that
as well with the high level archetype I
sees especially the you know tech lead
generalist um the skill set in leading
an initiative that ad engineers are
contributing to there's probably a lot
of leadership skill overlaps with the
director so I see that um but I I wonder
though for some of the other archetypes
like let's say you went deep into the uh
you're a specialist in AI or something.
I'm wondering maybe that diamond doesn't
come back. Yeah, for some archetypes it
definitely doesn't come back. You know,
there are some people that are super
deep like let's say you're into like
query optimization for SQL queries,
right? You can go very very deep on
that. And I think in a way some
archetypes going that deep on the
technology might not need to have
developed all the other skills that are
related to leading teams and whatnot. it
and may not be a good uh transition into
managing. You mentioned that you
navigated the conversation. You were an
E9 um and you sought out a demotion to
E7 and for those who don't know E9 is a
distinguished engineer and E7 would be a
senior staff engineer which are both
crazy high levels. How did you navigate
that conversation like requesting a
demotion?
Yeah. Yeah. This is a great question. I
was even concerned about it when I was
first promoted from an E8 to an E9 as
the site director of London. What I told
uh Facebook CTO back then, Shrep was,
you know, I'm very concerned that uh
because I like being an individual
contributor, I'm very concerned that I
cannot maintain this level of
performance when I want to move back.
And what he said to me during my
promotion to E9 was, "Hey, let's worry
about that problem when it happens. like
let's not not promote you because you
think one day you're going to want to go
back uh to coding. So when I went back
to coding I very much understood that I
was at a level that I in no way could
meet the expectations. And so I think
under those conditions, it felt honestly
great for me to ask to be uh moved back
to E7, which is the level I joined the
company at like eight years before that,
you know, um because I knew that I could
perform at that level and I definitely
did not want to be compensated more than
I deserved uh relative to my peers um on
a team. It feels so much better to be
performing well at a level than it feels
to be like barely treading water at a
level that you feel a lot of imposttor
syndrome in and that you're not even
sure that you'll stay long-term
qualified for. Right? So I actually very
much welcomed the change. Um but I think
also many people don't make a change
that big first of all and second of all
many people don't want um don't want to
take all that comes with that right like
for instance I went from being the site
director of a site that was probably you
know four or 500 people um down to
reporting to a manager who reported to a
manager who was then part of a
management of the site right and so like
you have to have an ego that is very
willing to say like hey I'm happy to be
just a member of a team down here um
doing my own work. And you also have to
be sensitive to other funny things like
you have to be careful not to speak up
about your opinions about all sorts of
things that you used to have opinions
about when it came to running the site
because you need to support the new
people running the site in being
successful. Like you need to support the
new leaders, right? By playing your role
on the team as opposed to using your
outsiz influence from the path to get
things done. And so I think both of
those things were changes that I was uh
you know willing to try to learn to
navigate and I very much welcomed being
leveled appropriately relative to my
contributions. Makes sense. And you
talked about the uh expectations being
too high for E9. Can you give a high
level like what what does it generally
mean for what is an E7 typically doing
or E8 typically doing or E9 typically
doing?
Yeah, great question. And I have to
caveat my opinion about this relative
to, you know, I was working at Meta
starting 15 years ago, right? Um, and so
my data about how those levels map is
going to be very coarse grain, right?
But in general, I think here are a few
important concepts just when it comes to
all those levels, right? Is it is about
the scope of the person's influence. So
like how big or how long uh or how
valuable of a project can you
single-handedly guarantee the delivery
of? Okay, so like an intern can not even
guarantee the delivery of a feature
necessarily, right? Um or they might
guarantee the delivery of a small
feature on time, right? A senior
developer like let's say an E5 E6 in a
company should be able to deliver the
work of about 10 people 10 to 15 people
right if you're regularly influencing
the work of 10 to 15 people and you can
reliably deliver things of that scope
when you are the one in charge for that
delivery whether it's technical delivery
or a product feature area or whatever it
is usually at E7 once again my data is
probably very stale I'd expect a person
to regularly impact act the work of
maybe 50 people, you know. So like um
you would be a person that is driving
technical direction for maybe around a
team of about 50 people. You are
regularly consulted on key changes on
that team by the product managers by the
engineering managers like you are viewed
as that influential right typically you
are able to personally deliver projects
on the scope of like six months. Meaning
like, hey, if I tell you this is your
goal and I don't have time to speak to
you for the next 6 months and I send you
off into, you know, the wild of coding,
you should be able to come back in 6
months with this thing done, right? Like
that is the scale and the scope of what
I'd expect a person to personally be
able to do, right? Um, as you get to
eight and nine, those things just
multiply out. And I think there's both a
quantitative change to it. So meaning
like I'd expect a director to regularly
influence probably the work of a hundred
people, you know, like that that's
around the scale that I would say seems
deserving, right? Um on the IC side, as
you know, people can be IC's that are
large scope in many different ways. They
can be large because they're very deep,
right? They're narrow, but they're very
deep, right? Uh they're deep in a way
qualitatively that others they can do
things others can't do. So like a great
E8 that's deep qualitatively that is
deserving of it for instance you cannot
simply replace him or her with like four
E6s and expect the same work like there
there's a level of work at which no
amount of adding people two levels below
is going to get the quality of work that
you need right so there are some jobs
like that there are some people that are
very broad so they are a jack of all
trades this type of person is especially
useful for nent teams or startup
startups, right, for small groups
because generalists are super valuable
there. And that's also because typically
you cannot hire three E6s that basically
can outperform one great generalist E8
that can like do a little bit of
everything, right? So there's a
quantization question there. Um, so
there's both a quantified difference,
meaning sides of team influence, but I
think the qualitative difference is
very, very important because those
qualitative differences often cannot be
articulated well in a bulletoint list
that your HR team sends you. And in
fact, if you go and try to do that
bulletoint list, you'll often be
disappointed that you're still not at
the level, and you'll be very confused
why not. It's because people at those
levels excel for very different reasons
and it take the judgment of a person
above those levels and these are hard
judgments, right? To decide whether or
not a person is deserving. So like let's
say you get promoted from an E8 to an
E9. When I worked back at the company,
right, E9 wasn't even a level when I was
first promoted to E8. Like it didn't
exist as a concept. Later the company
like it got hugely important people in
the company like John Carmarmac as a
good example as an individual
contributor right like what would you
level him at right so the company
eventually had to invent these levels I
think there was a period of time when it
was discussed when I was part of the
conversation of the first promotions
into E9 and my memory if my memory
serves correctly the company was
probably several thousand people at this
point and the company was considering
promoting three engineers into E9, you
know. Um, and so when you have that
small of a sample set, it is very hard
to create a bulleted to-do list of like,
oh, if you're E8, do these four things
and then we will like move you to E9.
Every one of those three people were
very different in shape. They were
different archetypes, right? They were
successful for different reasons. And
so, I do think that as you get higher up
in level, it's almost like how you
become a professor somewhere, right?
Like it's not like they have a bullet
list that says you published 10 papers
over three years in journals of this
quality and you're guaranteed tenure,
right? At some level it's all the other
professors believe you're a professor
then you're kind of a professor, right?
Same with these leadership level at like
eight and above in my opinion a lot of
it is would other E8 think you are an
E8? you know, for whatever reasons they
think that uh and those reasons are
different for people uh different
archetypes and they are hard to
articulate. And so for anybody who's
looking for a punch card to get there,
that's why it's hard to describe how to
do it with that dynamic then I kind of
wonder if there could be a chicken and
egg problem. Um so imagine you are a
excellent E7, but there are no E8s or
E9s in your vicinity.
Could you know could you even get that
qualitative input that says hey you're
solving problems that you know E7s can't
because you're just at the top of where
you are. Yeah totally especially at
small companies. So that happens all the
time to people who join small companies
or weak teams right both things can
happen. So let's talk about the latter
first. Uh Microsoft's a huge company.
You know when I worked there it was
140,000 people. Now before the layoffs
it was about 240,000. at 140,000 people.
This was like 15 years ago, 140,000
people is more than the populations of
40 countries in the world. So, you can
imagine like what that feels like to
work in a company that's the size of a
country. Um, in a company that size,
there are always weak teams. And the
problem with weak teams is on a weak
team, you may think you are awesome, but
that is because you work with very bad
peers. Okay? So like that will lead to
funny situations where people get
overleveled for instance. Um or it'll
lead to situations where people simply
do not have someone they can observe
that they can learn from because they're
on a weak team. They're like the best.
It's like how you buy real estate,
right? You never want to be the most
expensive house on the block because you
have no no room to grow up, right? Like
you you're already at the top. You don't
want to be the worst house on the block.
Nobody likes you, right? So you kind of
want to be the middle house, right? And
so you should find a block where you're
the middle house. Um, when it comes to
those higher levels, I do agree that
it's very hard to find great examples of
those people. And furthermore, each of
those examples excel in different ways
that might not be well matched to what
you're good at. Right? So I feel the
more important thing at those levels is
not necessarily another person to
observe, but a great coach that can give
you feedback. someone who is a decision
maker in the promotion of let's say an
eight to a nine and they can tell you
like hey qualitatively you're way off
from where we need you to be and then
you can have a meaningful discussion
about like oh what things can I do that
would be more like that right um so I
think it's much better to get that
qualitative opinion uh than to
necessarily find the right people to
model after so when you got promoted to
E9 um what was the project or the scope
just to give people a sense of you know
what does it look like if something gets
you to that level.
Yeah. I had brought 12 people with me to
start the engineering portion of the
London office of Meta, right? And so we
started off pretty small like that and
over a period of about uh four or five
years we grew it to a site of probably
four or 500 people, right? And so
through that growth, I managed several
key transitions on the site. So when you
start off with a site with 12 engineers,
that's super easy. Like a great
engineering manager at a level six could
do a solid job running that, right? But
as you grow with each order of magnitude
difference in the size of the team, the
complexity of the problems becomes much
harder and the solutions become much
less black or white. They become always
kind of gray in some direction. And so I
think the promotion was primarily
because I was handling a much wider
variety of things and much more key
strategic decisions. Let me give you a
concrete example. One of the last
meetings I had as a site leave was I was
trying to convince the people in Menllo
Park the number of interns they should
hire and the headcount they should have
in uh London this year for this summer
because I had done the math on the H-1B
anticipated volume for the following
year for full-time offers to metriculate
into Menllo Park. That does that make
sense? So I was having a conversation 18
months before the actual thing was going
to happen and I had used data to derive
what actions we should take today that
would only play out 18 months in. Right?
No one else was thinking about that.
Right? when I was more junior as an E8
in the site, I was the first one of all
of Meta's sites to really look at not
only ladder levels of all the engineers
but the pyramid of of of seniority and
to really think about like hey um do we
actually uh have the right seniority of
people? Are we growing people at a
commensurate engineering like growth
velocity, right? And so things like that
which are also much more about strategic
things than they are about um sort of
tangible concrete things to deliver. So
I think there are a variety of those
sorts of decisions that become larger
and larger in scope either in the
breadth of people they impact or in the
timeline forward in which you're
expected to think. Is there something
that you learned that uh really made a
difference in upholding a strong
engineering culture? Because you had a
very unique opportunity to take uh it's
almost like you started a company within
a company. What is it that really made a
difference in making sure that site was
very strong uh from an engineering
perspective? Yeah, great question. I
think one huge help to me before
starting the site was not only um did I
observe other sites. So I was the second
person hired in Meta Seattle and Meta
Seattle was Meta's first office outside
of its headquarters back then in Palo
Alto. So I had seen what it felt like to
grow from four desks into 120 desks by
the time I left. And I had learned from
some of the things we learned from uh
that were mistakes in how we grew that
site. Right. But more importantly,
before I actually started the
engineering office in London, I
interviewed site directors from other
companies at different sites. For
instance, one super helpful site
director was the former site director of
Google London, uh David Singleton, who
became Stripe's CTO um sometime after
that. Um he gave me some great advice.
The best advice of which was that Google
had experimented with what they call
landing teams. how many people you bring
to a site to bootstrap the culture and
whatnot. Um, our decisions on landing
teams were influenced by two things. One
thing was Shrep. Shrep said he wanted
two full interview loops of people,
meaning he wanted enough engineers for
two full loops. Okay, so that estimates
about 10 to 12 people, right? The thing
I learned from David Singleton was that
Google had experimented and Google's
takeaway was make the landing team
commit to two years minimum. Now, you'll
find many companies that approach this
differently. They'll have a landing team
show up for the first three months, the
first six months, and then the site is
on their own, right? I think that that's
a mistake because it is very difficult
to maintain culture in those early
growth periods where the percentage of
new people is like commensurate with the
percentage of old people that have been
around for like more than 3 months,
right? And so I brought 12 people with
me and I asked them to commit for two
years and that made a humongous
difference. The other big difference
culturally with the 12 people I brought
is I interviewed probably nearly 50
people in the company that volunteered
to go and I chose the 12, right? And one
of the ways I chose it is I interviewed
not only the people but somewhat of
their peers and definitely their manager
when it came to how they were good
culture carriers for the company. Like
would this be a good person to add to
the culture of the site? And I honestly
really locked out. The 12 people we
brought with us were amazing were
amazing people for building and
maintaining the culture of the company.
They had been at the company long enough
to know what its culture was. Right? I
also asked that each one of them be able
to bring over a project of some sort
because you also need someone that's a
able to lead work, right? And then you
have the exceptional talents like people
like Ben Matthews who were um individual
contributors that were very happy to
work on whatever the site needed but
could code the crap out of things, you
know, was just very very productive and
very astute when it came to how to hire.
So I really lucked out with the people
that we ended up choosing um to build
the site and so much of it was due to
learning from others who've done it
before. I see. And you said that you
wanted people to commit for two years.
Does that is that a verbal thing or is
there a um you know you get some
additional equity for staying or
something like that? There's no
compensation to it. So people got paid
whatever they got paid before, right?
And um we didn't make them sign anything
that said it it was two years, but I
basically had a serious conversation
with them of like, hey, I'm only looking
for people who are committed uh to at
least being there two years, right? So
if that doesn't fit in with your life
plan, this is probably not the job for
you, right? and and so um those folks uh
sort of elected self-elected off right
we had one person who needed to go back
sooner than their two-year one or two
people needed to go back sooner than
their two-year uh time commitment and
those were understandable reasons and we
just talked about it when it happened
and I was very supportive of them
transitioning but the surprise even to
me is far more people stayed much longer
than that in fact from the original
landing team I want to say probably
about four people are still in London
right now 15 years later like they are
basically British citizens, right? And
when they joined me in London, that was
not the plan. They they were not joining
me because they sneakily thought they
would become British citizens. Like they
ended up loving London. They loved the
office. They stayed committed. Right. So
I think in the end we also were very
fortunate to have people that were
committed like that without any sort of
real enforcement of it. You mentioned
that Shrep was your manager at some
point and I was when I was digging
through things I saw you had worked with
Bos as well and I imagine you had some
proximity to Mark Zuckerberg. Do you
have any favorite stories working with
any very curious because they're all so
legendary? Yeah. Um, you know, I was
very fortunate in working for a lot of
great people at Facebook. So, my first
manager was Bos, right? And Bos
eventually became uh the CTO. Um my
manager during the years of leading
London was Shrep, the then CTO. Uh both
gave me sort of great advice and
guidance.
Um I only talked one-on-one with Zach a
few times, so I don't really have too
much insight there other than um he felt
to me like he led the teams. He felt
very genuine to me in how he led the
teams. You know, one thing that
impressed me most about Zuck is, and
this is true of Bos as well, is you got
to remember when I joined the company, I
was 33 years old, right? The median age
of the company back then was 27. And so
I was the oldest guy in the Seattle
office for the first seven months. Like
a 33y old was literally the oldest guy,
right? And so most of the people I
worked for were actually younger than
me, right? Uh, but I was very impressed
with both Bos and Zuck in their ability
and willingness to personally grow. Like
in each of those cases, if you talk to
people that have worked with Bos for
more than eight or 10 years, right, or
with Zach for a good number of years,
they can tell you exactly how they grew
over time. It was very obvious that they
were not only open to coaching and
probably seeking it on their own, right,
but making a deliberate effort to
improve. Like small concrete example, if
you look at how Zuck ran AMAs um when I
first joined versus even two years into
my time at uh Facebook where I'd
randomly guess he was probably like 28
or or something. He had greatly improved
how he communicated at AMAs. So like uh
there were really neat thing. I'm pretty
sure for instance, small thing but I
noticed right I'm pretty sure someone
coached him on how to hold his head when
he was speaking in public. So when I
first joined Facebook, um, Zuck's
natural pose when talking was head
slightly upward. So he would look
slightly like this at the crowd, right?
But through the years, you saw him
deliberately correct that. It was very
obvious. He like deliberately corrected
it to where now he faces the crowd
straight on, right? And so I was always
very impressed by the things they were
very willing to improve in themselves
and put effort into.
You mentioned some of the highest level
IC's. The qualitative feedback from
people around them is a really important
aspect. I'm curious from your
perspective, having worked with a lot of
Meta's, you know, highest profile
IC's, is there someone that stands out
to you that consistently impressed you?
One person that I worked uh only ever so
indirectly with so barely with uh John
Carmarmac obviously legendary right but
the thing when you work in Oculus that
you realize is not only is he super
prolific in coding okay so he produced
so much code but he had an ability to
drop into your codebase and product
after not looking at it for like six
months and give actual concrete advice
about what to do like I was working on a
very tiny product called Oculus 360
photos. Very simple product. Um, and uh,
just one random day like John dropped
into the codebase and he tried it out
and he like had had insights about like
the distortion on the corners of the
photos like when when when you turned
and he had some performance ideas for
like, hey, I I think we can speed up
performance like this. And this is all
without anybody a asking, right? But b,
like he said some really smart things
that um, just no one on the team had
thought of. So that was impressive, but
I didn't work with him as directly. A
great example of an interesting shape
person, um, Scott Renfro. So I worked
with him a bit more because he came out
for a rotation in London for 6 months.
One thing that you'll find consistently
is peer feedback about Scott's work on a
team is super glowing. Like when Scott
reviews your uh, PR, right? Even if you
do something very dumb, he will put it
in a very sensitive way, not to shame
you or anything. So he'll say it in a
way that you understand what he's saying
is like, hey, this thing could be done
differently, right? But he'll never
publicly shame you or anything like
that. If you look at peer feedback for
him, it is overwhelmingly like Scott
takes time out of his day to make me
great. So he was an example where um I
think his uh seniority was welld
deserved in the company because it was
very obvious that having him on the team
would make your entire team much better.
So he was a force multiplier for teams
and later on he led these huge things
for meta. I'm pretty sure he had
something to do with GDPR at some level
and like a few other things like huge
infrastructurewide like massive changes.
And so he was capable both personally of
guaranteeing a huge scope of work,
right? But he was also a force
multiplier for the teams he was on. So
kind of a slam dunk case of someone who
deserved to be uh rewarded well for that
work. Coming to the end of your your
tenure at at Facebook or Yeah, it was
Facebook at the time. I I remember I
joined in uh 2018 and I had been there
for some amount of months and I heard in
the echoes of workplace that someone had
bought the entire company coffee for a
day and you know now I I've read a lot
of your posts and I know that was you.
What what made you want to buy everyone
at the company coffee for a day and
spend over $23,000?
Yeah, great question. I'll I'll start
with the original story which was
several years into my time at Facebook.
Uh Facebook had moved into um its
current location in Menllo Park. Uh
Hacker Square wasn't fully paved yet.
Eventually a field coffee opened there.
And one Christmas I just thought, well,
let me buy everybody a coffee for
Christmas, right? So for that Christmas,
for one day, I had paid for coffee for
everyone. And I just felt it was such a
joyous thing to see how happy people
were to get a free coffee from someone,
right? And after that day, the CEO of
Phils had written me to say that his
employees really enjoyed the the day a
whole lot because it had never happened
in their history, like something so
crazy, right? And so I felt like it was
a sort of a pay it forward sort of thing
that made me feel great, that made
others feel great. When I left the
company, I really felt like, you know, I
loved the company so much and the
company gave me so much over time. Like
gave me the opportunity to do really
interesting things, gave me incredible
coaching, right? Um when I joined the
company, a brick of money fell on my
head, right? Like I did not join
Facebook. People forget when I joined
Facebook, the big talk was still like
Friendster was coming back, G+ was going
to roll over Facebook. Like there was
all sorts of talk. Uh and eventually
like Facebook would never make money on
mobile. like there was a lot of like
rock throwing, right? And so when I
joined the company, I had uh no
expectations for what would happen. I
had left Microsoft um after working at
Microsoft 12 years. The stock had gone
up 15 cent in those 12 years, you know.
So I had um sold my 78s of unvested like
remaining shares for $1,600 and I went
to the company store and bought like an
Xbox 360, a driving wheel and fortza 3
and I was thrilled, right? So, the fact
that a brick of money hit my head, not
by my own design, but really just by
being lucky, right? Um, made me so
grateful, you know, what I did when I
first when Facebook IPOed, I gave 100%
of what I made from the IPO to charity,
you know, cuz I felt like it was not a
thing that I deserved, honestly. And I
don't mean to poo poo myself. Like all I
mean is like I was lucky enough to be
born in a time frame where my interest
in computer science actually paid
something versus if I worked for a
blacksmith 400 years ago, right? Um and
I happened to have migrated to America,
land of opportunity, right? So I felt
super lucky. And so what I wanted to do
was given the great experience at Phils
that first time with Christmas when I
left the company, I felt like I want to
give something back, you know, for all
the things the company has done for me.
And so what I did was I coordinated with
the major sites that had employees. So
back then it was probably five different
sites I thought of coordinating with and
I just called the individual owners of
the coffee shops in those places uh and
arranged a way to pay for coffee for a
day and it was super fun and really
rewarding to do and I'm really glad that
I did it. Yeah, it I mean it definitely
left an impression. I think everyone me
and all my friends were kind of new
grads at the time and you know it was
kind of this uh fun little thing. I I
don't remember if it was attached to
your name at the time. I think we just
thought it was someone nice at Facebook
was paying. So, you know, it was
appreciated for sure. So, when you
decided to leave Facebook, I'm curious
because it sounds like everything was
going quite well. What What was your
rationale for leaving? Yeah, great
question. The biggest thing on my mind
back then was I was very concerned about
the rising income gap in America. And so
I wanted to start a BC Corp to bridge
the rising income gap. I had a few ideas
for how to do that. Uh back then in
2018 I was also like this doesn't sound
revolutionary now but back then I was
complaining to co-workers that I think
we're going to experience technical
unemployment you know and back then that
term hadn't even really come around but
I I was convinced that robots would
replace people and that our society
needed to change quickly to adapt to
that and so most of my co-workers
disagreed but I felt very concerned
about it so I thought I should actually
do something like start a BC Corp to try
to do that. And so one of the main
reasons that I stepped down was that I
felt like Facebook had grown to a point
where um it would be fine honestly
without me like plenty more than fine.
It was doing really well. Um and I was
concerned about this thing happening to
America. I think another thing if I were
to evaluate myself having left the
company at the same level as when I
joined, right, is I feel like I was much
more useful as an individual contributor
when Facebook was small. When I joined
as the second person hired in Seattle,
Facebook had 500 engineers globally at
that point, right? Um but that meant
that I along with two other engineers
could ship the entire video calling
feature you know from nothing to
shipping um in a period of probably six
months right um I'm a generalist not a
specialist so I was also able to like
help with the negotiation of things like
what does the Skype contract say I
helped uh negotiate and hire and manage
the contractors that were testing on it
so I was capable of doing a very wide
variety of things eight years after that
time the company had grown to I mean
just thousands of engineers right um the
company had grown to a point where I
think a generalist like me is much less
useful you know than specialists and so
I also felt that my unique value
contribution was no longer the same you
know I I I was a very generic coder um
and I wasn't contributing anything that
was exceptional honestly uh and so I
also felt like I was much less effective
for the company would you say that's
generally True. So, you know, taking it
out of big tech, imagine someone wants
to work at startups. Would you say the
generalist skill set is the way to go?
And, you know, specialists can have an
edge at the largest companies. Yeah,
that that's my intuition is that most
small companies value generalists more
than specialists. Like, every small
company can use definitely one
specialist. Like, no matter what domain
you're in, right, you probably want at
least one person who really knows that
that domain super well, right? But I
think most of the times what you deal
with in small companies and is
quantization effects. Like if your
company is large enough, you can hire a
PR comms person who's full-time job 40
hours a week is to handle comms, right?
But before you're that large, it's very
difficult to hire a part-time three
hours a week comms person, right? And so
you kind of tap some product manager on
your team that's pretty good with
communication and you ask them to handle
it for a while, right? So because of
these quantization effects, I do think
generalists are more purposeable in
those cases of fractionalization, right?
You can fractionalize a generalist um to
a bunch of different roles, but
eventually a company gets so large that
each uh fraction of work that needs to
be done is probably uh you know
warranting one or more employees
full-time on it. In which case having
the generalist is kind of like a lot of
wasted energy, right? Because they are
only you know only 15% of their skill
set pertains to the actual work you're
doing.
So at some point once you left uh
Facebook and then you pursued um the BC
Corp, I saw that you did you came back
to the industry for a little bit to join
OpenAI. Um I'm curious what's the the
story behind you coming back to
industry. Sometime after quitting
Facebook, I ended up starting a local
nonprofit in Seattle called Outere that
builds free software for global health,
you know, and this was funded by the
Gates Foundation. Um, and the software
is deployed, I think, in Nigeria, Kenya,
and South Africa, and it helps with
assisting um, uh, rapid testing for
malaria. Okay. Um, that work was simply
because I didn't expect to have a grant
from the Gates Foundation. I felt very
fortunate and lucky to have been chosen
to get a grant for that and I felt like
building some free software for global
health seemed like a great idea and so I
really enjoyed that work. Um after that
I took a break for a while where I was
unemployed and I think part of that
during that time I had started using a
lot more of GitHub copilot in VS Code
back then trying to evangelize to
friends that hey this AI thing like it's
it's useful but I had a hard time
convincing people to join back then uh
to pay for it. Um and so when AI began
to really take off, you know, sometime
in the time frame of maybe chat GPT3,
five or four, um I felt like, wow, this
is this is a huge transition point in
the industry. I feel like I missed two
major transition points because I was at
Microsoft. First of all, I missed the
whole.com thing because Microsoft as a
whole missed the internet revolution,
right? And so that was a massive thing.
The second thing was the mobile
revolution. Microsoft largely missed
that as well. And I was at Microsoft
when that happened. And so I felt very
fortunate to have caught the social
network revolution, right, which was a
huge transition point in humanity. But I
increasingly felt like AI would
potentially be as big or maybe bigger
than the internet's impact on humanity.
Because from a universe perspective, we
might be the first species to create
something smarter than us. And from like
an evolutionary perspective, that's just
really weird. Like that goes second
order like once that happens, right? is
like what is actually happening in the
universe right we might answer the firmy
question right and so I felt like this
transition was something I didn't want
to miss the reason I joined open AI was
what I learned from working at Facebook
is I would much rather join the market
leader or nobody at all and here's why I
think the market leader has room to
experiment because it can afford to fail
at a few things this is what I
discovered at Facebook with a big enough
market lead you can take some brave big
shots because like if two things fail
and Facebook had some big colossal
failures too, right? But you have enough
of a lead to do it. Usually the market
follower like Google+ as a good example,
right? Usually the market follower their
formula has to be match all of the
leaders checkboxes and have one unique
thing you think is going to be
differentiating. In the case of Google+,
the thing was circles. This idea that
you might want to manage circles of
friends that are different. Okay? But to
have a social network, you had to do all
the basics that every other social
network did, right? So, I feel like
especially number TWs, number threes
might might be able to do crazy hail
Marys, but number TW's, the problem with
number TWs is their whole schedule and
timeline is dictated by the leader.
Like, they have to be fast follow,
right? Um whereas number one gets to
blow a lot of time on crazy things and
and I love the craziness. So that's why
when I look to join AI, I only applied
to o to open AAI. My plan was I either
joined that or I'm still going to write
my own software. I see. And when you
joined OpenAI, how did it compare to to
uh Facebook?
Great question. I had joined Facebook at
a different stage in its growth. When I
joined Facebook, it was 500 engineers,
right? when I joined Open AI, I want to
say it was about 120 engineers. So like
qualitatively that is very different. Um
so with that caveat in mind, um it is
really the highest talent density of any
group of engineers I've worked with. And
so it was really amazing and that after
when I shifted from Microsoft to
Facebook, I felt like Facebook was a
huge jump in quality of engineer on
average of the person that I worked with
and there are just amazing people.
especially in early Facebook, it was
like full of amazing people. Um, I felt
like OpenAI was even a notch above that.
And so, um, it was really amazing the
people I got a chance to work with, uh,
and to learn from. What are the things
that made you see how amazing it was?
Was it the technical abilities or
something else that really stood out to
you? Yeah. Uh, people had exceptional
technical capabilities. I I would say
one thing that Facebook always had a lot
of that I believe OpenAI is going to get
increasingly better at is I think
Facebook always focused a lot on
product. You know, like what is the
product? Why do people use it? And I
think there's a way in which like
because Facebook did not honestly have
much magic sauce beyond a network effect
and a great product people love using,
right? Um it causes you to work on it.
Whereas I would say in the early chat
GPT days when there were no viable
competitors, right? You kind of could
have a lousy product, people use it
anyway, right? And because like you you
might remember like a year or two ago,
it's very common for like every fourth
conversation thread to have an error
like a server error and then you like
reload the thread and you rerun it,
right? You can get away with that when
nobody else is producing anything near
as compelling. But I think as
competition heats up, people will begin
to see that ultimately products are what
make things, not pure research, but
actual research shipping in compelling
products is what makes for success.
Yeah. Yeah, definitely. I I agree. The
early days of Chat GPT, it was uh so
special that you you put up with it and
now people are catching up of it. Um,
one thing I wanted to ask you and I
think this is because I, you know, am a
fan of your writing and I've read so
much of it. What I've seen is that your
your writing ability is a superpower of
yours and I know writing is important
for software engineers. It gets you a
lot of leverage. I'm curious how how did
you develop that skill? Were you were
you writing from a young age or is that
something you developed at Microsoft?
Um, yeah. What tips do you have when it
comes to writing? I was bad at writing
at a young age. The main reason that I
was bad at writing when I was uh even
through college is I very much did not
respect the value of good communication.
Like I came from a culture that
respected getting A's and everything and
like I felt like there were hard
sciences and then everything else was
flop. So if you made me take history, if
you made me take English, I felt like
this was a waste of time. These are
subjects with no right answer. it's all
like people's opinions, right? And so I
had a very sort of um low attitude
toward the soft skills and so I did not
respect the soft skills and so I didn't
invest in them. So I was a bad writer,
right? Over time I think I lucked out in
that when I started work at Microsoft um
in some of the spare time I had, I just
started rereading some of the classics,
you know, and these are things that in
high school when assigned I I really
hated them, right? the these are all the
classic like Hemingways and then Great
Gatsby and like stuff like this. And I
started to see these books in a
different light. Like I was a bit older
so I could appreciate more of what was
said in it. And I also started to really
develop a love of the language, right? I
think it was Virginia Wolf that said um
to write well you need to read well. And
so I think first of all is you got to
read well, right? And so the types of
sentences that someone like David Foster
Wallace DFW can put out, the types of
sentences um that he can put out are
amazing. If you read Alice Monroe short
stories, right? The language is
beautiful. Pilgrim at Tinker Creek, like
there all sorts of amazing books where
when you read it, you feel like, wow,
the language here is exceptional. So I
then started to really respect that that
was a skill, you know, and that was a
valuable skill, every bit as valuable as
a hard skill, like a science skill. And
so then I started working at it. And a
lot of writing better, I think, is not
only reading well, but really being
willing to rewrite multiple times. So
many of the posts that you've seen me
make, I have rewritten multiple times
before posting them, right? And so being
willing to have some things um on the,
you know, cutting room floor, right? Uh
is also um pretty important. Even now
when I read people's subf facts for
instance, I once in a while do notice
something and I try to remember it like
oh this way of saying something
rhetorically was very clever. So I'm
going to try to remember that this is
one way you can communicate an idea. Um
and so I think that has also helped but
most of all I think was my willingness
to not disrespect the skill and to
actually see it as an essential skill
for uh even for scientists for technical
people I think is hugely important. Yeah
definitely and what what you said about
growing up and not respecting the softer
subjects definitely resonates. I have
very similar value system when I was
growing up and now I see the value of
writing and so that's why I'm kind of
into it. Um some of the stuff that you
wrote too um for instance your essay and
I guess this is only only people at Meta
could see it but the your essay as good
as it gets um your the creativity to
kind of jump around and give a
nonchronological narrative I thought was
really cool. you're jumping around your
life and just getting the feel of a
bunch of things and some of the things
that you communicate are not it's not
even a full, you know, narrative bit,
but it somehow gets the idea across. I
really liked that. And um I'm curious,
do you have an editor when you were
writing or that's all from you
continuously reading and rereading?
Yeah, that thing was a moment of
inspiration where I thought how do I
tell this story, you know, like what is
a compelling way to tell this story? And
most often like the compelling way is
chronologically actually because that's
the way that makes sense, right? Okay.
But some stories I think work better out
of chronological order because you see a
different arc that's developing in a
person's life, an arc that's actually
like threaded, right? And so that's what
I felt for that uh particular story.
I've not had an editor for any of those,
but one place where I did hire an
editor. Um it it was great. I hired a
lady named Rebecca Ambrose to edit my
podcast, Peak Salvation. And the big
thing about that is I knew I wanted to
do a miniseries and I wanted the words
to be well structured. I wanted the
story to be told well and I knew that a
professional would do a much better job
at editing. And there I learned a ton
from Rebecca. Like if you listen to
those episodes, you can tell that oh,
someone who works in the profession has
has like given feedback on this, right?
And so I have gotten feedback in those
cases, but nothing ever that I've posted
professionally was edited by another
person. I see. Yeah, your essays are
legendary. I think I sometimes I go back
to visit them and I'll see they're still
alive. People are commenting saying,
"Oh, I just found this. This is great."
Or, "Oh, you should reread this." Big
fan. So glad you put those out. Thank
you. And um the the great by the way the
great post explorer I I it was alive as
of maybe twoish years ago. I think
someone took it down at this point. I
tried to before we did this I was like
looking for it. I'm curious how did that
side project come along? Yeah. So I
wrote a thing inside the company
Facebook called the great post explorer
which was meant to like rank and expose
people to some of the most commented on
or the most reacted to posts of all time
within the internet of Facebook. Right?
The main reason I wrote that was I
benefited from discovering
serendipitously great things written by
people who came before me in Facebook
that I wish were somehow cataloged
somewhere and not only cataloged but
like crowdsourced in how they were
categorized because I wanted to be able
to navigate it by categories, right? And
so I built that thing with that hope.
And so the whole purpose of it was the
realization that um you know Slack has a
worst case of this but but Facebook has
this which is like posts fade temporally
but in my opinion posts values the value
of a post is often temporal but in some
the cases of some posts the value is not
temporal like this is just like some
podcasts you know are evergreen and some
podcasts talk about current news and so
to me I wrote the great posts explorer
as a as a chance for people to discover
some amazingly timeless things that
people have posted in the past. Part of
writing well is reading quality stuff.
And that's also what made me want to go
deep in there cuz you essentially
created a curated set of quality posts
where all of Meta was helping you
curate. And so yeah, I loved that when
it was up. Um I'm not sure what happened
to it. Coming to the end, I just want to
ask you a few reflections on your career
that might be helpful for some people.
So, the first thing I wanted to ask was
when you were young, you prided yourself
on fast execution speed. That was
something that set you apart, at least
from I tell your your writing, and then
later you were more of a leader. You
slowed down in the execution. I'm
curious. Do you do you find that
software engineering is like being an
athlete from the perspective of you have
some performance peak at I don't know
exactly what for an athlete it's
probably late 20s or early 30s and then
there's a performance decay or or do you
think that you know you continue to
develop experience in software
engineering doesn't have that cap?
Yeah, I feel like you can get more and
more valuable over time. Now everybody
has an asmtote and everybody's curve is
probably asmmptoic meaning like you
probably have a phase in your career
where growth is easy and then everybody
has a final level right um everybody's
final level is different by the way
right and and so as you approach that
you should feel like the growth is
slowing however just as with work hours
beyond 50 or 60 right I believe each
incremental growth can still be growth
so like I don't think you have to stay
fixed and you're a flatline forever Um,
I think here's the thing. When I was
young, I would outrun everybody, but I
was running serpentine basically, right?
Um, as I've gotten more experience, the
idea is to jog in a straight line,
right? And how does a senior experienced
person jog in a straight line? Part of
it is an experienced person usually gets
society sense for when things aren't
headed the right direction and they
either don't pursue that thing or they
convince that team to stop that early.
like they basically save an entire
team's worth of time because they're
like, "Hey, I feel like we're heading
this direction." I've seen this in the
past. One of the things that can happen
is this concrete example. I had a friend
who worked at Microsoft who was telling
me that the product he was working on,
the vice president of the organization
met with them every week to triage the
bugs towards shipping. And I told him,
look, if your VP is in triage meetings
on a weekly basis so that you can ship
on time, your project is nowhere near
shipping on time. like this thing is in
a huge flame ball like this is a huge
problem right I don't know how people
that experience can live through that
and not see you know how obvious it was
to me that that thing is like a bad sign
right this is a tell that your project
is not on track um but I think you
develop that sense of like oh this is
worth investing in this is not worth
investing in I think the other way you
grow your scope over time is I think you
begin to
value everybody running in the same
direction even if the direction is 3°
off ideal. You know, when I was young, I
had this idealism to me. So, I felt like
there was a right direction to go and
like two degrees off was like wrong, you
know. But the problem is a whole team
pulling 98 degrees correct versus like
half the team pulling 100% correct and
the other half debating them on like
which is correct. I think the team
pulling together is going to get
further, you know, and like that was
wisdom over time of saying like even
though I don't agree with a 100% of what
this is what Amazon means by disagree
and commit, right? Is like there are
times you need to disagree and commit
and like that is valuable in itself. And
so I think some of that wisdom I I
continue to develop. But when it comes
to for instance a young person's ability
to outwork me is definitely true now.
Like I do not have the physical stamina
I had when I was 24. If you woke me up
at 3:00 a.m. today to start coding, I
would code very slowly at 3:00 a.m. Like
when I was 23, if you woke me up at 3,
it was no problem. I I I would just get
going, right? So I do think that some
things get weaker and hopefully if we're
growing like other things get stronger.
At the beginning of your career, it
sounds like you you were kind of
leaprogging people to some extent. you
became a very young manager and
management is often seen as a a
profession where your reports need to
respect you and there might be some
unusual dynamic because of the age
difference. Let's say you have older
people reporting to you. I'm curious how
did you win the respect of these people
as such a young manager?
Yeah, this was difficult and I think
that I both lacked humility when I was
younger and I was overly ambitious for
myself. And so as a concrete example, I
would not have worked for my 24 year old
self, you know, but I was so ambitious
that I was one of the team's strongest
engineers. So when I asked to manage
people, people were like, well, he was a
good engineer. Like let's not, you know,
make him unhappy. Let's like have him
manage people. Right? In that first
year, I had to as a 24 year old, I had
to fire a 40-year-old and that was very
difficult. Like firing people never gets
easier. Like hopefully like hopefully
you aren't like the eye of Sauron and
you delight in firing people. But like
that was exceptionally difficult and it
was in my opinion made more difficult by
my self-awareness of just how junior I
was relative to this person. You know
what I mean? And so um now he did
deserve to be fired. He was not
performing to the level of expectations
that we had of him, right? But he was
also a person that was two levels above
what my level was and I was managing
him, right? And so like I was too
immature to know how to manage people
more experienced than me. Like that's
its own sort of maturity is how do you
manage someone who's a higher level than
you are, you know, like how do you even
do that successfully is a tricky thing,
right? So I did a very poor job of
managing and so I was a a pretty um bad
manager but I was so obsessed with
growth that I was also a huge sponge for
learning. So I was constantly getting
mentors to grow in some area. I would
ask for feedback like how can I do this
better? I would read a lot of
non-fiction about things like managing
teams about what conversations like all
sorts of things right. So I was doing a
lot of self-improvement over time. So I
do think that I grew over time but I was
always like the start was pretty rough
and and I've had a lot of things where
I've managed poorly. Even in my last
year of managing uh people you know I
made some huge mistakes. So for instance
uh one of my biggest weaknesses when
managing people is I am very bad at
giving feedback you know. So like I um
pull punches when I give feedback. I
resist giving feedback because I hate
the the the awkward feeling of
confrontation, right? And so I resist
giving feedback. When I give the
feedback, I try to downplay how
important it actually is and so people
don't understand how serious it is. And
so I continue to be bad at doing that. I
think over the years I've gone from very
bad to like pathable, you know, but that
is not an area where I expect to become
uh, you know, excellent. Whereas I do
think I am much better at motivating
action. So I think when I lead a team,
whether I'm a manager on a team or an
I'm an individual contributor, you know,
I only join teams that I believe in and
when I believe in something, I'm very
passionate about it. And I think
communicating that passion and that
vision excites people to do the work. So
I think I am good at that. Uh but there
still are a lot of things to to improve.
We talked a little bit about generalist
versus specialists and sounds like you
you're you identify as a generalist. I'm
curious how did that play out over your
career? And let's say there's some new
grad or someone earlier in their career,
they're they're thinking, should I
become a specialist or a generalist? How
would you make that decision? Yeah, that
I think is a tricky decision depending
on how well the person knows themselves.
So there's the occasional exceptional
person like these prodigies in chess for
instance, right? They will have been a
prodigy by the time they're eight or
nine years old and so they're obviously
fit to play chess. that person should
specialize because that's like
unnaturally unique talent, right? Most
people aren't like that. Most people do
not like from age seven have a solid
like thing of like I am very good at
this. I should do this, right? And so
for most people, I would caution against
early binding too much to a specialty.
You know, there there are two dangers to
binding too early. One is how do you
know you're a specialist and not a
generalist without being a generalist?
Right? So that that's part one. Part two
is you have an idiot soant risk, right?
Is like you bound so early to a
specialization like Erdish, a famous
mathematician, um even as an adult did
not know how to cut his own grapefruit
with a knife. So his mom would cut his
grapefruit, okay? But this was an
amazing mathematician that published
tons of papers, right? But he
specialized so early he can't even cut
fruit. Okay? So like that to me feels
like over specialization. But he did
some amazing work in mathematics, right?
So I feel like if you are a 22 23
starting your career, I would in general
encourage at least dabble in a few
things before you like die hard commit,
one last risk to committing to a
specialty way early in your career is
what if that specialty is going away,
you know, especially in the age of AI,
this is something to think about. It's
like if you join some company and you're
diehard committed to like technology A,
right? um what if in three years that
thing becomes irrelevant and that's all
you know you know you're like the cobalt
person like hoping like Y2K happens
again right is because cobalt's not used
anywhere but that's your specialty so I
think specializations come with that
danger that generalists don't suffer
that danger I guess the last question
that I'm curious about is after this
career that you've had if you were able
to go back to the beginning when you
just entered the industry
and you give yourself some advice based
on everything that you know today, what
would that advice be?
Yeah, great question. I have a few
thoughts that I share. One, Roy Disney
said, "Decisions are easy when your
values are clear to you." Right?
Decisions for me a lot of times were
hard because I didn't have clear values.
If you know exactly where you're going,
decisions toward getting there become a
lot easier. So, one advice I would give
my younger self is spend a little more
time thinking about what you actually
want, right, before you commit to doing
these things. I think another thing is I
often feel like I was the dog that
caught the car, you know, like I was
convinced when I joined Microsoft that
what I wanted to be was a dev manager.
Okay? And so for my first eight years or
so, I would take any job that would get
me a step toward that. So, one,
decisions were easy then cuz it was
like, well, does this job get me a step
closer? Yes, it does. Then I'll take it,
right? But once I caught that car, you
know, once I hit that level, once I
recognize that, hey, E7 might be my
terminal level. This might be the
highest I ever get in my career. Um, the
problem with peaking early, you know,
because I hit that level when I was
probably, I don't know, 20, you know, 30
years old or or something like this,
right?
Um, the problem is you're like a child
actor. Like the question is what are you
going to do with the rest of your life?
Like if your whole plan is acting and if
nobody hires you for acting, you're
going to be in a world of hurt. Like you
you are not going to enjoy the next 40
years of work. And so for me, I I was
the dog that caught that car. And I had
no mental model for like once I became
the death manager, which I did become
right at a very young age. Once I became
a level 67 and I became that at a
relatively young age, it was sort of
like
well like what happens next? And I
really went through a period of pretty
serious depression because I felt like I
had lost a purpose to life. Like life
seemed to have so much meaning and
direction when I had a clear goal. But I
caught the car, right? And then it was
like what to do. So the other thing I
would caution my young self about is to
just be sure you actually want the thing
you want. You know what I mean? Like one
thing I tell people now is, you know,
would you want to be Warren Buffett? You
know, so many people love the billions
of dollars, but he also in is in his
late 90s. Like would you want a few
billion dollars and be in your late 90s?
Like is that worth it? Is that what you
want? Like this is an interesting
question, right? So, I think for me now,
I think a lot more about um am I even
going a direction I want to be at when I
get there, right? One final thought that
I'll leave with you with the sleeping
bag business is sometimes you bend the
read, sometimes you break the read,
right? Sometimes things break and they
aren't fixable. So, when I had sleeping
bags in my office, uh my fiance came out
to Seattle to visit me during that time.
When she visited me in Seattle from
Maryland, during that time, I would see
her every evening at 11 p.m. when work
ended. That was when I would go see her.
So, basically, I got to eat like a late
Denny's dinner with her from 11:00 p.m.
to like midnight. And that was my plan
for my visiting fiance, right? I am very
fortunate and lucky that she is my wife
now. But anybody I tell that story to,
you could bet nine out of 10 times
that's the story that ends with that's
how I got the engagement ring back,
right? Is how that story ends, right? I
did not realize that some reads bend and
some reads break and I was clearly
bending something to an extreme that
most things would have broken, right?
And so I do think that in one's life,
back to your point of like what should a
diehard person who only cares about
career do? like what is the absolute
fastest way to like get there, right? I
would say a be sure that's what you
want, right? Don't be the dog that
caught that thing and then you regret
catching the thing, right? So, a be sure
that's really what you want. And part B
is
like, you know, be sure you're com
comfortable with other things breaking,
you know, because like that is what it
will take to get there if that's truly
what you want. So my advice to my
younger self about that period of time
would have been, you know, in net
getting to level 67, getting to an E7
when you're 30 versus 38 in the big arc
doesn't make any difference. Like beyond
38, I still have 30 years of work to go,
right? So it's like how fast do I want
to be at my terminal level? Like what's
the real plan there versus can I keep a
healthy relationship with my spouse,
with my kids, right? That's important.
And so that's what I would advise back
then. Yeah. It's funny because I I think
maybe this is the type of advice where
looking back it's obvious, but I wonder
if you right now could talk to that
Philip that was grinding, you know, at
26 or 27. Would you even accept the
advice? It's hard to say. I feel like a
lot of people who are fully focused may
not. Well, I feel like it's easy to say.
I feel like for me the answer would have
been no, I would not have accepted the
advice. Because here's the thing, like
everybody tells you money doesn't buy
happiness, right? Like when when someone
with $3 million tells you, trust me,
money will not buy buy you happiness. If
you're an unhappy person now, you're
going to be an unhappy person that can
spend a lot of money uh you know, 10
years hence, right? But nobody believes
it, right? Like everybody thinks, "Oh
yeah, yeah, yeah, but when I'm wealthy,
I'm going to be happy, right?" Everybody
thinks they're the exception to that
rule. So I agree with you completely
like advice feels good to give because I
feel like maybe I'm saving someone from
something but in reality 90% of the
times you have to be ready to receive
the advice for the advice to have any
impact and I was at a maturity level
that was nowhere near ready nowhere near
ready uh to receive that advice. So I
would not have benefited from my own
advice for sure. Well yeah Philip thank
you so much for this. I mean, I was
really looking forward to this
conversation and I learned so much. I
uh, you know, really appreciate your
time. This is this is awesome. I'm going
to polish this up, make it really good
for others so they can enjoy it, too. Is
there anything that you wanted to shout
out to the audience? Maybe we can
redirect them to something that you're
working on. One of the things I might
recommend just because I'm still
concerned about technical unemployment
is people might give my podcast
miniseries Peak Salvation a spin. It was
about my time working at Amazon's
flagship warehouse over peak season from
Black Friday to Christmas. Right? I feel
like in there I was able to explore a
lot more of my concerns around
automation, what it means to society as
a whole, the income gap in America and
its rise. Right? I do think that as
Americans, we need to get together and
like figure out how we help the average
person through this change. I think as
you know in technology, the change is
going to be massive. it's going to come
sooner than people expect and then very
bad things can happen if we don't help
the whole society adapt to it. So I
would encourage people to like think
about that maybe give the podcast a
listen which might give you different
perspectives about it. Um and hopefully
you know figure out a way to contribute
to making that better. I will put that
in the show notes. So if you're
interested in listening to that take a
look at the show notes. I'll put it in
there. Cool. Okay. Well thanks so much
today Ryan. This was great. Oh yeah. I I
mean thank you. you're the one that I I
want to thank. This is really great.
I've been wanting to have this
conversation for a while. So, really
really appreciate your time. Yeah. And I
appreciate the effort that you put into
making these valuable to other people.
So, thank you for putting that
investment